This is where you accepted the Nobel?
Yes.
Like right here. Right
Here.
Tell me about that moment.
Well, it was in the heart of the pandemic,
and normally it's done
in Stockholm, Sweden,
and so the Nobel Committee
said, well, we're going
to send the Nobel to you,
and we're going to give
it to you in your garden.
When you wake up the next day,
does the world just open up,
or do you feel a weight of responsibility?
If I'm honest, I mean,
it was so overwhelming.
I didn't go into science
with any thoughts of winning prizes.
Believe me. You know, I just hoped I
could get a job someday.
My husband said to me, well,
now your main job is being
an ambassador for science.
And I thought, how do I do that?
Being the face of a scientific revolution
is a lot of pressure.
Even for Jennifer Doudna,
a legend in biology
who helped turn CRISPR
into a breakthrough method
for altering DNA, tackling
everything from genetic disease
to climate change
and spawning dozens of
companies in the process.
But some critics claim
the tech hasn't lived up
to its hype just yet.
Not to mention the ethical concerns.
At the same time, movie depictions
of biotechnology haven't
exactly been great
PR for gene editing.
More human than human is our motto.
It didn't matter how much I lied,
my real resume was in my cells.
So to get to the real
story, I went to Berkeley,
California to meet with
Professor Doudna to talk about
where CRISPR is actually headed.
I do have a sense that
over the next three years,
we're going to see some
continued breakthroughs
To parse through fact versus
fiction in the AI race.
I'm not seeing chatbots in
our own experience innovating
And to gauge how excited
or worried we should be.
So do you feel a sense of urgency?
Oh, yeah. Every day. Yeah.
So this is your famous garden?
Well, such as it is, yeah.
How much time do you spend back here?
Not enough is the answer.
But I love being in my garden, Emily,
because it's a way I refresh my mind.
It's amazing how when I come up here
and I'm, even if I'm just
pulling weeds, I feel connected
to nature in a way that
I find very relaxing.
Doudna's Nobel origin story began
in the rainy town of Hilo,
Hawaii where her family
moved when she was seven.
What inspired you there
when you were growing up?
Well, let's just start with, nobody in my
family was a scientist.
I haven't found a single
scientist on either side
of my family, but I remember
how fascinated I was
with just the beauty of the place,
and I think that was one of the things
that first got me interested in science,
was thinking about why,
you know, different plants
and animals were able to
survive there and thrive there.
When she's not untangling
life's biggest questions in her backyard,
Doudna is teaching, running a lab,
mentoring young scientists
and advising startups looking
to turn her life's work
into real world cures.
Today, she took us inside the
Innovative Genomics Institute,
a research hub she founded
that's part breakthrough
lab, part startup incubator.
It's fun, right? Yeah.
I still kind of get chills
when I come in the lab. Yeah.
You know, I, I love the feel of it.
I mean, I still remember my
first time going into a research
lab and feeling this sense
of wonder, you know, kind
of the sense of discoveries
are being made here
and wanting to be part of it.
I can't believe I never realized this,
but it was pointed out
to me that your name
literally spells do you DNA.
I mean, that has to be fate.
It has
to
be fate, right?
I had to work on this.
So what kind of research
is happening right now?
Well, we've got all
kinds of work going on.
We're doing some very
fundamental science trying
to figure out the
original ancestral origins
of Crispr in bacteria, which
is where it comes from.
I'm really excited about
all the students and
and postdoctoral trainees that are here
that are doing really
creative, interesting science.
I can't tell you how many
times they come up with ideas
that I would've never thought of.
So recently, a person
in my lab figured out
that he could extend the efficiency
of Crispr in a whole organism.
He's doing experiments in
a mouse model of disease
by simply accelerating the
pace at which Crispr molecules
are able to edit cells.
Wait, let's pause here for a moment.
Crispr, we've been talking about it,
but we should probably explain exactly
what it is and how it works.
Right. Okay.
The discovery began with Doudna
and her collaborator,
Emmanuelle Charpentier
and their obsession
with the remarkably adaptive
immune system inside bacteria.
When a virus attacks a bacterium,
the defending cell saves a
fragment of the viral DNA
and turns it into guide RNA,
which is like a tiny genetic GPS.
If the virus returns a
protein called CAS-9, kind
of like molecular scissors pairs
with the RNA GPS then locates
and cuts the invading virus.
The breakthrough from Doudna
and Charpentier was realizing
this guide, RNA GPS,
could be reprogrammed
directing CAS-9 scissors
to cut genomic sequences beyond viral DNA,
including human cells.
Suddenly editing DNA was
no longer theoretical.
And over time, Doudna launched a bevy
of biotech companies out
of IGI, all working in different ways
to translate Crispr technology
into treatments for patients.
Give us a sense of the scope
of, you know, the number
of companies and new ventures
that have come out of IGI.
So, from the very beginning
of the institute, one
of our goals was to ensure
that we had a pretty smooth pipeline
between fundamental discoveries
and the kind of organizations
like startup companies
that would be able to
build real world value
around those discoveries.
I think we've now spun out
31 companies at last count,
$9 billion valuation.
If you add it all up, over
2,500 jobs created largely here
in California, but elsewhere too.
It's, it's really extraordinary.
Long before founding IGI,
Doudna spent years studying RNA
at Harvard and Yale,
but it wasn't until 2006 at UC Berkeley
that she turned her attention to Crispr.
Were there nights that you couldn't sleep
because you felt you
were close to something?
Oh, yeah. It had that kind of
detective story feel to it.
You know, when you're hot
on the trail of something,
you know that it's very
exciting, can't wait
to do the next experiment.
Crispr was very much that way.
What are the current use cases
that inspire you the most?
Well, I always think about Victoria Gray,
who was the first patient
with sickle cell disease
to be treated with Crispr
here in the United States.
Her story is so inspiring.
Victoria Gray, an activist
and lecturer is the first
person with sickle cell disease
to receive an experimental
treatment using Crispr.
I want to reach others
who feel like no help
is coming. We're coming.
Do you have patients reaching
out to you all the time?
All the time.
So you're getting a lot of calls?
We do, yeah. I'll just say
that I, I always thank people
for reaching out because
they're often sharing very
personal stories.
They're taught, a lot of them are about
children, you know, their kids.
A lot of people will send
pictures of their children.
It really brings home the
importance of what we're doing,
and frankly, the need to work as fast
as possible on real therapies
that can benefit people.
So do you feel a sense of urgency?
Oh, yeah. Every day? Yeah. Yeah.
Because every day that
passes, you could be coming up
with a miracle cure
or
saving someone's child.
Or
just
realizing
that there's still a big divide
between the kind of work that
goes on in a lab like this
where we're making fundamental discoveries
and actually taking that knowledge
and having it benefit people.
In a real sense, there's a big gap there.
So far, Crispr therapies like those
for sickle cell have been
built to treat entire groups
of patients with the same genetic disease.
But in 2025,
a new milestone was
achieved at the Children's
Hospital of Philadelphia,
when an infant known as baby
KJ became the first patient
to receive a fully personalized
Crispr based gene therapy.
He was born on Thursday. Friday morning,
they had said to me, your
son is very sick. In patients
who have urea cycle disorders,
they can't break down protein.
And what happens is ammonia builds up
and ammonia can be toxic to the brain.
We didn't know that we were gonna reach
his first birthday.
Now we're seeing him crawl.
Now he's walking now he climbs
on everything under the sun
and thinks he's the most
funny person in the room.
Baby KJ's treatment shows a
glimpse of what's possible.
But the therapy came with a
price tag of around $800,000,
supported by a patchwork of
public research, funding,
academic collaboration and philanthropy.
How's baby KJ doing?
My understanding is that he's doing great.
You know, he's continuing to grow.
He's continuing to benefit from the,
the Crispr treatment that he received.
It's an extraordinary story.
So how do we save more baby KJs?
Right?
That's the question, right?
It can't be a path that
costs millions of dollars.
takes a huge army of,
of people and time to achieve.
I'd really like to see a world
where we can diagnose
people quite quickly,
who have rare disease,
quickly figure out if they
might be a good candidate
for a genetic therapy like Crispr,
and if the answer is yes, then
have a very smooth pipeline
for making the CRISPR
therapy, testing it quickly,
and then getting it into the patient.
One way Crispr research may accelerate is
with artificial intelligence,
which could theoretically
help scientists design edits
faster and predict their
risks more accurately.
That promise has already piqued the
interest of Silicon Valley.
A huge fraction of chatGPT
queries are health related.
So we wanted to get really good at this.
One day, maybe we can cure all
disease with the help of ai.
It'll look like there's a human professor
and a thousand AI grad students,
and they're smarter than
you are. By the way.
Doudna is less gung-ho on the matter.
Biology's hard, that's all.
I guess it really comes down to that.
You know, I've been working in,
in this area for a long time
as a biologist,
and the more I learn, honestly,
the more I'm really humbled
by the fact that, you
know, biology is complex.
We're not going to be
able to simulate our way
to an understanding of the human body.
We're not going to be
able to avoid the need
for certain types of testing.
I do think there are opportunities
to increase the efficiency
in which we make discoveries
about the way our bodies work
and the way they interact with
drugs that will be effective,
and I think AI will be helpful there.
But it's gonna come down to
training models on the right
kinds of data, and a big need for better
and more data for training
models if we wanna achieve that.
An OpenAI executive recently suggested
that if a discovery happens on chatGPT,
let's say a drug discovery,
that OpenAI should get a cut of sales.
What do you think of that?
Good luck.
Expand.
How are chatbots going
to change drug discovery?
I'm not sure the answer
to that yet. I don't know.
Lots of people are of
course, very, very hopeful,
some very hopeful about it.
But I think that innovation
is still really in the domain
of human beings right now.
I'm not seeing chatbots in our
own experience, innovating.
They can be helpful with summarizing data.
They can be helpful in writing reports
and things of that nature,
but I'm not seeing chatbots
coming up with a brand new idea
for something that nobody
else ever thought of.
So you're saying AI can't innovate?
I don't know if it can't innovate.
I just don't think it is right now.
What about after the AGI moment?
Well, I never say never.
So maybe that'll happen, but
I'm not holding my breath.
Well, there are just so
many big promises out there,
like Larry Ellison saying,
AI will cure cancer in a 48 hour window.
Does that hold any water?
Believe me, I'd be
overjoyed if that is true.
We all would, but I just,
I don't see it right now.
Doudna's mission is to turn
Crispr from a scientific
breakthrough into real world medicine,
but commercializing gene
editing means delivering those
edits to the right cells
safely, reliably, and at scale.
So Crispr was supposed
to usher in this era
of miracle cures, and we've seen some,
but was the promise of
overstated, or are we just early?
I think it's a classic
example of, you know,
this happens a lot in in human nature.
You know, we get very excited
about something, a discovery
or a breakthrough of some kind,
and you start imagining all
the possibilities with it.
And then as you start to to
dig in, you realize that,
you know, there's still some challenges.
I mean, think about the human
genome being sequenced back
around the year 2000.
Now we're in 2026, so we're
26 years from that moment,
and yet honestly, we still
don't understand the function
of about 40% of the genes
in a typical bacterial cell
with a much smaller genome
than the human genome.
That just gives you a
little bit of a sense
of the complexity.
We recognize that it's a
very powerful technology,
but it has limitations that
have become clear over time.
What are the limitations that still exist?
A lot of it has to do with the way
that we put Crispr
molecules into patients.
Right now, it's being done
mostly by therapies that,
or strategies that involve
taking cells out of the patient,
editing them in the lab,
and then transplanting them back in.
And you can imagine that's quite involved.
It's quite expensive. It's
unpleasant for patients,
you know, it's not ideal.
So I think going forward,
increasingly there are efforts
to turn Crispr into what
we call an in-vivo therapy
or a therapeutic, where we can
deliver it directly into the
patient's body in a way
that will take these editing
molecules to the right cells
where they do their job and
then don't do anything else.
Is there a time horizon that
you like to look at in terms
of when, I don't know, there,
there will be some sort
of feeling that the
sky has been the limit.
It's always hard to put
a timeline on things.
I do have a sense that
over the next three years,
we're going to see some
continued breakthroughs.
Two, three years isn't,
isn't too far away.
Not too far away.
Yeah. So what happens in two, three
years?
Yeah, for one thing,
I hope that we're able
to treat more patients like KJ
and provide a path for others.
We'd like to get more medical
centers involved in this
type of an approach.
We'd like to drive down the
cost, of course, partnering
with manufacturers
that can make the molecules
we need more inexpensively,
and really just getting
more clinical teams
involved in this effort.
I think if that can be done,
then there's really going
to be a path to opening the door
for many more rare diseases to be treated.
But these large scale efforts
require hefty resources.
And over the past year,
federal funding cuts under
the Trump administration have
created significant uncertainty
for long-term scientific research.
Over the past three years,
the number new grants
from the NSF dropped 24%,
and roughly 25,000 scientists and staff.
About 20% of the workforce
have left federal
research agencies.
We're a year into the
Trump administration.
A number of grants have been cut.
How does science fair in
the age of President Trump?
We're seeing real,
real challenges right now,
as you just mentioned.
You know, I think the, the cuts
that we've seen really
risk the economic success
of the United States in, in science
and technology in a way that
is, to me, very unfortunate.
We've been a leader in science
since the second World War.
On every dollar that's been
invested from the NIH in
research leads to about $2.50
of economic benefit.
That's a pretty darn good
return on investment.
So giving that up, I think
seeding that to other countries
because they will, they will
step in, you know, there,
there are opportunities there.
If we don't continue our investment in
science, others will do so.
I think that would really be a shame.
But the Trump administration's
impact on science goes way
beyond these cuts.
What do you think of the MAHA movement?
Is it gonna really make
Americans healthier
or something else?
Look, I think, you know,
health decisions need
to be made based on data
and based on science.
And there's a reason why
people train in medical schools
or they go to graduate
school to learn about how
to evaluate science or
to evaluate clinical data
or to work with patients.
And I think we have to lean into
that when we make health decisions.
Do you know RFK JR?
I don't.
If you had an audience with
him, what would you say?
I'd say what I just said to you,
What are your concerns about
where this leads, you know,
there's the MAHA movement,
there's the anti-vax movement
coming from somebody who
worked on RNA, which was a key
to the COVID vaccine.
It's a dangerous moment.
It's very dangerous.
I mean, when I see things
like measles outbreak in
South Carolina, it's terrible.
It doesn't have to be that way.
When you're in a room alone
with scientists, you know,
what do you privately discuss?
Like what are people
saying about this moment?
Well, I think there's a lot of concern.
I think that many of us feel,
if I'm honest, also a sense
of responsibility that we need
to be better at communicating
the value of our work.
Why it's publicly funded.
Why should taxpayer dollars
be used for research?
What's the value of what we do?
And there's incredible value,
but we haven't maybe been very good
as a community at
communicating that to people
that are not scientists.
Does it ever make you wanna scream?
Yes, but you know, then
Emily, I look around
and I think, you know, I
work at an incredible place
and I feel also incredibly grateful.
We talked a bit about biotech funding.
Researchers say they're
considering leaving
the United States.
What are the implications of
this? Does China surge ahead?
I think it maybe does, at least initially.
I think that's a possibility.
I think it's a very real possibility
because at the same time
that the United States is
pulling back on funding,
we're seeing a, you know,
a big investment in science in China.
Over the past decade,
China's biotech industry has
rapidly accelerated, propelled
by state backed investment
and a streamlined path
for human trials in 2018,
amid this climb,
a scientist based in Shenzhen
conducted a widely condemned
gene editing experiment.
The Chinese researcher has
created an international
controversy after claiming he
helped make the world's first
genetically edited babies.
The procedure raised fears of
a new era of designer babies
with parents selecting
traits for their children,
A possibility that remains
largely theoretical,
although maybe not for long.
You've said, we'll see Crispr
edited babies within 25 years.
What kind of edits and
who are these babies?
Those decisions are
gonna be made by a, a lot
of the people who are coming of age and,
and coming into re their
reproductive years.
I think because it'll be a
question of assuming that we get
to a point where the
technology is actually safe
and effective for that kind
of purpose, then asking
what kinds of edits should we make?
And who should have
access to that technology?
Who should be paying for that technology?
Who should be regulating that technology?
Those questions really haven't
been answered at this stage.
I know people of reproductive age now
and thinking about some of
these things, the companies
that are promising they can select embryos
for traits like intelligence
and other things.
It's part of what's been
called the Silicon Valley push
to breed super babies.
We look at something like
height, even eye color,
hair color, intelligence, intelligence.
What's actually possible
now and what's not possible
because aren't these
traits that are controlled
by thousands of genes?
Yes. So I agree.
I think it's, I think it's,
it's a tall order to be able
to do that kind of
selection in an in vitro
fertilization clinic.
It's also, you know,
likewise going to be very
hard to know which sets
of genes would need to be
edited to give you a, an outcome
that affected intelligence, or
something as complex as that.
So I just don't see it anytime soon.
There's this concern if
you select for one trait,
let's say intelligence,
that you might also end up
getting a lot of undesirable traits.
Well, you know that you're touching on
something that I think about a lot.
You know, all the genes in
our cells are interacting
with each other in ways that
we mostly aren't aware of
and don't understand yet.
And that means that if we tweak one gene
or even a few, we can't always be sure
what the outcome is gonna be,
especially if we're looking
long into the future.
So I think that's gonna continue
to be an area where we need
to do research.
You know, clearly that work is
still at a very early stage.
They're working in mice and
you know, they're working in,
in systems that, you
know, they haven't gotten
to the complexity of a human body yet.
So let's say it becomes
increasingly possible.
On what grounds can we tell
parents, you can't do this?
Like, why wouldn't you want
to engineer babies to be
as healthy as possible?
Some people might say, well, I'd like
to edit out the sickle cell
trait, which, you know,
I think one could make
a very good argument
for wanting to do that.
On the other hand, if a parent
said, I want to, you know,
change something about eye color or height
or musculature, you know, that, you know,
some people might feel that
it's not appropriate in the end.
I think it's gonna come
down to probably putting
applications of Crispr
into different buckets.
You know, where we could
imagine one bucket would be
for diseases that are devastating,
where we have a very
well-defined genetic cause
and a clear way to make the
targeted change in the genome
that would prevent that with
Crispr versus other things
that have a lot of risk
associated with them,
where you might need to be
changing many sets of genes that,
as you said, would potentially lead
to unintended consequences.
You've been called the
moral compass of biotech.
Does it ever feel more like a
burden and less like an honor?
And do you ever miss the sort
of quiet joy of discovery?
Yes, I miss the quiet joy of discovery.
I'd be lying
if I didn't admit that,
but these are kind of the
cards I've been dealt in my
career, and so I try to embrace it.
I try to learn from it.
I try to use it as a way to, you know,
to ultimately make sure
that CRISPR is gonna benefit
as many people as possible.
What began with innovation
in a lab has grown into an
entire Crispr industry,
startups, pharmaceutical giants,
and now AI driven companies,
all converging on the next
phase in gene editing.
But for many, the biggest concern isn't
failure, it's success.
Do you ever struggle with
unleashing this power on the
world, this potential to do so much good,
but also it's really scary.
I guess I don't tend to
think about it that way.
I, I tend to think about it
in terms of the opportunities
that Crispr brings,
but I also recognize that
there's a responsibility
to speak out about the
potential risk at the moment.
Certainly I feel very excited
about where it's headed.
The opportunities to treat
people that have rare disease,
I think is, is here
potentially opportunities
to prevent diseases that affect many
of us in the future is coming.
So is it paradise ahead or Gattaca?
Maybe somewhere in the
middle, Emily, you know,
hopefully closer to Nirvana.
There's this perception of
science as this sort of slow,
methodical process,
but your journey has had so
many dramatic twists and turns.
Who plays you in the movie?
I hope it's Kate Winslet.
I like that I'm a fan. Is there a movie?
I haven't heard of one,
but let me know if you hear
otherwise.